Nothing to be ashamed of. There's full transparency.
沒什么丟人的，所有一切都必須透明 （國會議員波特高斯）
...in any way, shape or form.
…都沒什么讓我感到羞愧的
I have a 1-800 number. Call me.
我這里有1800門電話，打給我 （不是真的）
I'm the guy you call if there's a violation or an abuse.
如果發現有違反和濫用該法案的情況，打給我 （他的私人辦公室的電話）
If you've got a poster child on this, I wanna see it.
如果你有現成的例子，拿給我看
I'm hired by the people to provide oversight. I provide oversight.
人民雇我提供監督，我不能白拿俸祿
Trent Lott said, the day the bill was introduced:
特倫特 洛特（參議院多數黨領袖） 說 該法案實施的那一天
"Maybe now we can do things we've wanted to do the last 10 years."
“也許我們就可以去做 過去10年一直想做的事情了”
No, a dictatorship would be a heck of a lot easier, no question about it.
不，毫無疑問，獨裁容易得多
I mean, they had all this on the shelf somewhere.
他們早就有這些想法 （國會議員吉姆 麥克蒂馬特）
Ideas of things they would like to do. And they got 9/11...
有許多想做的事情，現在有了9/11…
...and they said, "It's our chance. Go for it."
…他們說，“這可是個好機會，不能放過”
There was an assumption of the administration...
政府這么假設… （約翰 孔葉斯 眾議院司法委員會成員）
...that there had to be a surrender of certain of our rights.
…我們必須在某種程度上放棄一些權利
There's troubling definitions in the bill.
該法案在一些定義上模糊不清 （泰米 鮑德溫眾議院司法委員會成員）
The definition of terrorist, it's so expansive...
對恐怖分子的定義太寬泛…
...that it could include people who... - Like me.
-…因此有可能包括-- -我
No one read it. That's the whole point.
沒人看過它，問題的關鍵就在這里
They wait till the middle of the night, drop it in the night, print it in the night.
他們一直等到半夜 半夜敲定，半夜印刷
And the next morning when we come in, it passes.
早上我們一到，就通過了
How could Congress pass this Patriot Act without even reading it?
國會怎么可能連一項法案看都沒看過就通過了呢?
Sit down, my son.
別激動，孩子
We don't read most of the bills.
大多數法案我們都沒看過
Do you really know what that would entail...
如果每一項所通過的法案…
...if we were to read every bill that we passed?
…我們都要細加審閱，你知道意味著什么嗎?
Well, the good thing, it would slow down the legislative process.
說輕了，會減緩立法進程
I couldn't believe that virtually no member of Congress...
我無法相信事實上沒有一個…
...had read the Patriot Act before voting on it.
…議員在投票前通過愛國法案前讀過它
So I decided the only patriotic thing to do...
所有我認為我所能做到的唯一愛國行為…
...was for me to read it to them.
… 就是讀給他們聽
Members of Congress, this is Michael Moore...
國會議員們，我是邁克爾 摩爾…
...I would like to read you the U.S.A. Patriot Act.
…我將給你們念美利堅合眾國的愛國法案
"Section 1:
第一節：
Section 210 of this code reads as follows..."
第210節…
"Section 2703C..."
“270節3C….”
My job is to secure the homeland. That's exactly what we're gonna do.
我的工作是保護國土安全
But I'm here to take somebody's order.
但我來這里是聽你們點菜的
That's you, stretch. What would you like?
你，你要點什么?
- Right behind you. - I'm gonna order some ribs.
-就在你后面 -我要點肋骨
We all know you can't secure the homeland...
我們都知道，你不能空著肚子 保護國土安全…
...on an empty stomach. And in order to remain secure...
…為了安全起見…
...everyone needs to sacrifice.
…每個人都必須做出犧牲
Especially little Patrick Hamilton.
特別是小帕特里克 漢密爾頓
I'm sure each of us has our own airport-security horror story.
我相信每個人都有機場安檢的可怕經歷
But here's my favorite.
下面這個是最有趣的
The terrorist threat that was posed by his mommy's breast milk.
他媽媽的奶水居然也成了恐怖威脅
I thought if I put a little bit on my lips, that would be sufficient...
我想只要我稍微嘗一下就夠了…
...because I'm tasting it. She looked at me, and I felt like...
…她（安檢人員）看著我，我覺得…
...she was telling me, "Chug that." She goes, "You need to drink more."
…她的表情仿佛在說“喝一大口” 果然她說“你得多喝一點”
And of a 4-ounce bottle, I wound up drinking...
結果4盎司的奶…
...2 more ounces of breast milk...
…我被迫喝了兩盎司…
...that then, because it's touched my lips, has to be tossed.
…最后，因為碰過了我的嘴， 只好全部倒掉了
While homeland security was making sure breast milk...
為了國土安全，母乳不能…
...was kept off our planes...
…帶上飛機…
...they were also doing everything possible to ensure no one...
…同時也不能攜帶任何火種上飛機…
...could light a firebomb onboard.
…以免點燃火焰彈
- I can bring that on the plane? - Actually, yes, you're fine.
-那個可以帶上飛機嗎? -可以的
One too many books of matches.
多了一盒火柴
You can have four books and two lighters.
你只能帶4盒火柴，兩個打火機
When we already have the shoe-bomber...
目前已經發現鞋炸彈攜帶者… （巴朗 龍 參議院航空附屬委員會成員）
...who would have blown up an airplane...
…按照FBI的說法，如果他有丁烷打火機…
...if he had a butane lighter, according to the FBI...
…就可能會炸毀飛機…
...why would Transportation Security say it's okay...
…那么為什么交通安全法又規定…
...to take four books of matches and two lighters...
…可以攜帶4盒火柴兩個打火機上飛機呢？…
...as you board a plane? I'm guessing somebody put pressure on...
…我想一定是有人施加了壓力…
...to say, "When an airplane lands, people wanna light up...
…他們說旅客一下飛機就會迫不及待想抽煙…
...so don't take their lighters away."
…別沒收了他們的打火機 （這些人就是煙草商）
Let me see if I got this straight.
你們聽聽我說得對不對
Old guys in the gym, bad. Peace groups in Fresno, bad.
健身房的老頭，壞人 弗雷斯諾的和平組織，也是壞人
Breast milk, really bad.
母乳，那就更可怕了
Matches and lighters on the plane? Hey, no problem.
火柴和打火機？沒問題
Was this really about our safety? Or was something else going on?
真的是為我們的安全著想嗎? 還是有其它什么原因?
This is where the Pacific Ocean meets the shores of Oregon.
這里是俄勒岡州的太平洋海岸
Over 100 miles of beautiful, open coastline on our border.
邊界線上100英里美麗開闊的海岸
And, thanks to the budget cutbacks...
多虧了預算削減…
...the total number of state police protecting it:
… 保護這漫長海岸的州警的數目是:
One.
一個
Part-time.
還是兼職
Meet Trooper Brooks.
我們來認識一下布魯克斯警官
I maybe get a chance to hit this stretch of highway...
我當班的時候，大約一周兩次…
...once, maybe twice a week during my shifts.
…上這條高速巡邏
You know, just to even drive up here and look.
也就是上來轉轉
You know, I mean, as far as I know, there's lots of things they could do.
就我所知，有很多事情要做
I don't even wanna suspect, because it just makes me ill inside.
我想都不愿意去想，因為那樣會讓我難過
Back at the state trooper patrol office, thanks to the budget cuts...
來到州警辦公室，還是多虧了預算削減…
...Trooper Kenyon had to come in on his day off...
… 肯警官不等不休息天加班工作…
...to catch up on some paperwork.
…以趕上工作進度
For the most part, especially during summer, when people show up...
大多數時候，特別是夏天…
...this is what they get. They close the door.
…人們到這里來都會吃到閉門羹
They can read the sign about the office closure.
他們會看到一張公告
It just basically explains that due to our cutbacks...
簡單說明了因為預算削減…
...our office is not open for administrative business.
…辦公室被迫關閉
There's a sign that explains when the office is closed...
這里還有一個說明，辦公室關閉的時候…
...they can use the phone booth to get in touch with our dispatch.
…他們可以用這個電話聯絡我們
Ironically enough, that phone is a piece of junk.
可笑的是，這部電話根本是垃圾
It doesn't work very well, so half the time...
時好時壞，因此有一半的時間…
...they pick up the phone and dispatch gets static.
…他們拿起電話，只能聽到噪聲
They don't hear anything.
其它什么都聽不見
For Tuesday, there'll be no troop on patrol.
星期二則沒有州警巡邏
Wednesday, there'll be no troop on patrol.
星期三也沒有
Thursday, there'll be no troop on patrol.
星期四也沒有
You get calls all the time.
總是有人打電話來
People will call in a suspicious vehicle...
報告可疑車輛…
...or somebody looking suspicious.
…或者可疑的人
And I don't hardly ever respond to that anymore.
我現在几乎不回應了
I just don't have the time to do it.
因為沒有時間
I asked, "How many people do we have in Oregon...
我問他們，今晚在俄勒岡…
...on duty tonight?"
…有多少州警在執勤?
And we had eight troopers...
答案是…
...on for the entire state of Oregon, working.
…在整個俄勒岡州，只有8個
I think Oregon is a prime example that homeland security...
我想俄勒岡州這個典型例子說明…
...is not as secure as what people would like to believe.
…我們的國土并不像人們想像的那么安全
Nobody's sent me a manual that says, "Here's how you catch a terrorist."
沒有人給我如何抓恐怖分子的手冊
If I had that manual, I'd read it. But I don't. So...
如果有的話，我一定會讀，但是沒有…
Yeah.
是啊
The Bush administration didn't hand out a manual...
布什政府沒有分發…
...on how to deal with the terrorist threat...
…如何對付恐怖威脅的手冊…
...because the terrorist threat wasn't what this was all about.
…因為恐怖威脅并不是這樣的
They just wanted us to be fearful enough...
他們只是要我們感到恐怖…
...so that we'd get behind what their real plan was.
…那樣我們就無法識破他們的真正目的
Four minutes.
4分鐘
- Right from the top. - All right.
-從上面開始 -好了 （2003年3月19日10點11分）
- How much time? - Three minutes.
-還有多少時間? -3分鐘
- Okay, folks. - Thirty seconds.
-好了 -30秒
- Stand by. - Fifteen seconds.
-准備 -15秒
Ten, nine, eight, seven, six, five...
10，9，8，7，6，5…
...four, three, two, one.
…4，3，2，1
My fellow citizens...
同胞們…
At this hour, American and coalition forces...
此時此刻，美國軍隊和聯軍…
...are in the early stages of military operations...
…開始采取行動…
...to disarm Iraq...
…解除伊拉克武裝…
...to free its people and to defend the world from grave danger.
…解放它的人民，消除對世界的威脅
On my orders, coalition forces have begun striking...
根據我的命令，聯軍已經開始…
...selected targets of military importance...
…有選擇的打擊重要軍事目標…
...to undermine Saddam Hussein's ability to wage war.
…削弱薩達姆侯賽因發動戰爭的能力
On March 19th, 2003...
2003年3月19日…
...George W. Bush and the United States military...
… 喬治 W. 布什和美國軍隊…
...invaded the sovereign nation of Iraq.
…入侵了主權國家伊拉克
A nation that had never attacked the United States.
這個既從來沒用攻擊過美國
A nation that had never threatened to attack the United States.
也沒有威脅攻擊美國
A nation that had never murdered a single American citizen.
更從來沒有謀殺過一個美國公民的國家
We're going to find this... I think this piece of my neighbor.
我們要弄清楚-- 我認為這塊殘尸是我鄰居的
Young girl, age 20.
一個20歲的年輕女孩
I think it's the other part of her body. That's all.
這恐怕是她的另一塊肢體
There is a lot of innocent civilians that were killed.
大量平民傷亡
And I think that is because the U.S. Army...
我想是因為美軍…
...we came in, and we knew it wasn't gonna be easy.
…我們沖進來，覺得不會容易
And pretty much at first shot anything that moved.
一開始就向所有移動目標開火
When war happens and fighting starts...
戰斗打響之后…
...it's like we're pumped up, motivated, ready to go.
…我們信心百倍，士氣高昂
It's the ultimate rush.
這是一場決戰
Because you know you're going into the fight...
你知道自己要去戰斗…
...then you got a good song playing in the background.
…聽著背景的歌曲
And that gets you real fired up. Ready to do the job.
你覺得熱血澎湃
You can hook your CD player up...
你可以用坦克的…
...to the tank's internal communications system.
…內部通訊系統播放CD
When you put your helmet on you can hear it through the helmet.
帶上頭盔就可以聽到
This one we listen to the most.
我們最常聽的就是這個
This is the one... When we travel, we kill the enemy...
這個，我們前進，殺敵的時候…
Drowning Pool. "Let the bodies hit the floor"...
斃命水池樂隊 “讓尸體砸向地面”…
...is fitting for the job.
…聽這個最合適
We picked "the roof is on fire"...
我們挑了 “屋頂著火”…
...because it symbolized Baghdad being on fire.
…因為在我們要消滅薩達姆和他的政權的時候
At the time we wanted it to burn to get Saddam and his regime out.
這象征著巴格達一片火海
The roof, the roof The roof is on fire
屋頂，屋頂 屋頂著火了
We don't need no water Let the motherfucker burn
不需要水，讓這些雜種燒吧
Burn, motherfucker, burn
燒吧，雜種，燒吧
This is a totally different picture here being pushed into the city.
坐著坦克進入市區巷戰
Urban warfare in a tank.
看到的又是另一幅不同的畫面
Civilians.
平民
The civilians...
是的，平民--
You don't know who's friendly, who's the enemy.
你不知道哪些人對你友好，哪些人是敵人
This is a lot more real and true than just a video game.
比電子游戲真實得多
People thought it was gonna be, "Look through the sight and shoot." No.
有人認為就是瞄准開槍這么簡單，不
A lot of this is face to face.
很多是很直觀的
Especially riding by after some of the bombs went off...
特別是炸彈爆炸后…
...and seeing all the people on the side of the road bloated up.
…你在坦克里面看見路邊尸體飛上天
And all the smells around you from the people lying dead, rotted.
四周彌漫著腐尸的惡臭
It's a lot more gruesome than you think.
比你想的要可怕得多
We called in with some artillery and some napalm and things.
炮彈和汽油彈落下
Some innocent women and children got hit.
打中一些無辜的婦女和兒童
We met them on the road, and they had...
路邊隨處可見…
...little girls with noses blown off. And...
…被炸掉鼻子的小女孩. 還有--
And...
還有…
...husbands carrying their dead wives and things like that.
…背著妻子尸體的丈夫，諸如此類
That was extremely difficult to deal with. You're like:
非常難以面對，你會想
"Shoot. What the hell do we do now?"
“該死，我們都做了些什么?”
The targeting capabilities and the care that goes into targeting...
大家可以看到，精確打擊的能力 以及我們的謹慎態度…
...is as impressive as anything anyone could see.
…給人留下深刻印象
- Got him. - Good. Second one.
-打到了 -很好，第二個
Get the other one.
打另一個
The care that goes into it, the humanity that goes into it.
我們不僅謹慎，還注入了人道主義
Honestly, I think we should just trust our president...
說石化，我覺得我們應該信任我們的總統…
...in every decision he makes, and we should support that.
…支持他的每一個決定
You know? And be faithful in what happens.
相信所發生的一切
- Do you trust this president? - Yes, I do.
-你信任總統嗎? -是的
Britney Spears was not alone.
布蘭妮斯皮爾斯并不是一個人
The majority of the American people...
大多數美國人…
...trusted the president. And why shouldn't they?
…相信這位總統，為什么不呢?
He'd spent the better part of the last year...
去年他花了大半年的時間…
...giving them every reason why we should invade Iraq.
…告訴他們為什么要入侵伊拉克
Saddam Hussein has gone to elaborate lengths...
薩達姆 侯賽因花了大量的時間…
...spent enormous sums...
…大把的金錢…
...taken great risks to build and keep weapons of mass destruction.
…冒了很大的風險制造和藏匿 大規模殺傷武器
Saddam Hussein is determined to get his hands on a nuclear bomb.
薩達姆 侯賽因下定決心搞核武器
Nuclear weapon. Nuclear weapon. Nuclear weapon.
核武器，核武器，核武器
Active chemical munitions bunkers. Mobile production facilities.
打開化學武器倉庫，使用移動生產設備
We know he's got chemical weapons.
我們知道他有化學武器
He's got them. He's got them. He's got them.
他有，他有，他有
Huh, that's weird.
哈，真奇怪
Because that's not what Bush's people said when he first took office.
布什一伙剛上任的時候可不是這么說的
He hasn't developed capability...
（2001年2月） 他沒有發展…
...with respect to weapons of mass destruction.
…大規模殺傷性武器的能力
He's unable to project conventional power against his neighbors.
他沒有對鄰國發動常規戰爭的能力
Saddam Hussein aids and protects terrorists...
薩達姆 侯賽因資助并保護恐怖分子…
...including members of al Qaeda.
…包括基地組織成員
There was a relationship between Iraq and al Qaeda.
伊拉克和基地組織有聯系
Saddam. Al Qaeda.
薩達姆. 基地組織. 薩達姆. 基地組織
Saddam. The al Qaeda. Saddam. Saddam. Saddam. Al Qaeda.
薩達姆. The 基地組織. 薩達姆. 薩達姆. 薩達姆. 基地組織
It's only a matter of time before terrorist states...
恐怖分子的國家裝備大規模殺傷性武器…
...armed with weapons of mass destruction...
…并把它們運送到美國的城市…
...develop the capability to deliver those weapons to U.S. Cities.
…只是個時間問題
We're giving you facts and conclusions...
我們所提供的事實和結論…
...based on solid intelligence.
…都是建立在可靠情報上的
He's a man who hates America.
他恨美國
This is a man who cannot stand what we stand for.
他的信念和我們的相悖
There's willingness to terrorize himself.
我們必須以彼之道還施彼身
He hates the fact, like al Qaeda does, that we love freedom.
他和基地組織一樣痛恨我們熱愛自由這一事實
After all, this is a guy that tried to kill my dad at one time.
他甚至曾經想殺我的爸爸
They got people to believe there was a threat when in fact there wasn't one.
他讓人們相信子虛烏有的威脅
You get told things every day that don't happen.
你每天聽到的都是那些根本沒有發生過的事情
It doesn't seem to bother people.
人們卻并不為此煩惱
The Democrats were there to put a stop to all these falsehoods.
民主黨一直想阻止這些謊言 （參議院民主黨領袖湯姆.達斯勒）
I'll vote to give the president authority he needs.
我會投票給予總統他所需要的權力
United States is prepared to lead the coalition of the willing that will do it.
美國已經准備好領導聯軍的正義之師
When I say we will lead a coalition of the willing...
我說過如果他不愿意解除武裝…
...to disarm him if he chooses not to disarm, I mean it.
…我將領導聯軍的正義之師 來替他解除，我說話算話
- Who's in that coalition of the willing? - You will find out who's in it.
-你所說的正義之師是指哪些? -你們很快會知道的
The coalition of the willing.
正義之師
Roll call.
名單
The Republic of Palau.
帕勞群島共和國
The Republic of Costa Rica.
哥斯達黎加共和國
The Republic of Iceland.
冰島共和國
None of these countries has an army, or for that matter, weapons.
這些國家都沒有軍隊，因此也沒有武裝
So it looked like we'd be doing most of the invading stuff ourselves.
看起來動刀動槍的只有靠我們自己了
- Then there was also: - Romania.
- 還有 -羅馬尼亞
The Kingdom of Morocco.
摩納哥王國
Morocco wasn't officially a member of the coalition...
摩納哥實際上并不算聯軍的正式成員…
...but according to one report, they did offer to send 2000 monkeys...
但是據報道，他們愿意捐獻2000只猴子…
...to help detonate land mines.
… 幫助排雷
These are men of vision.
他們很有遠見
The Netherlands.
荷蘭
And I'm proud to call them allies.
我自豪地稱他們為盟友
Afghanistan.
阿富汗
Afghanistan?
阿富汗?
Oh, yeah. They had an army.
哦，是的，他們有軍隊
Our army. I guess that's one way to build a coalition.
我們的軍隊，我猜這也是建立聯盟的一種好方法
Just keep invading countries.
不停入侵別國
Yes, with our mighty coalition intact, we were ready.
是啊，有了這么強大的盟軍，我們枕戈待旦
One could almost say it's the mother of all coalitions.
可以說這是所有聯盟的典范
Fortunately, we have an independent media in this country...
還好在這個國家有獨立的媒體…
...who would tell us the truth.
…他們會告訴我們真相
The rallying around the president, the flag and the troops has begun.
部隊開始聚集到總統麾下
And we're gonna win!
我們一定會贏!
You have to be with troops to understand the adrenaline.
只有在軍隊里你才知道什么是勇氣
I want you to know, I think Navy SEALs rock.
我想你知道，海豹突擊隊真棒！
The pictures you're seeing are absolutely phenomenal.
你們看到的這些圖片都非常棒
When my country's at war, I want my country to win.
我的國家在打仗，我希望她贏
Iraqi opposition has faded in the face of American power.
在美軍的強大攻勢面前， 伊拉克人的抵抗開始崩潰
What you're watching here is truly historic television and journalism.
你們看到的是具有歷史意義的電視報導和新聞報導
It was absolutely electrifying.
真令人激動
They had to strap me in with my camera at the back of the plane.
他們不得不把我和攝像機綁到飛機背面
An awesome, synchronized killing machine.
一個了不起的同步殺人機器
There is an inherent bias...
總的來說，美國方面的報導…
...in the coverage of the American press in general.
…具有天生的傾向性
Am I slanted and biased? You damn well bet I am.
我是不是有傾向性？當然有
But one story the media wasn't covering...
但有一個方面沒有涉及…
...was the personal story...
…就是每一個陣亡士兵…
...of each and every soldier who was killed in the war.
…具體情況的報導
The government would not allow any cameras...
政府不允許出現…
...to show the coffins coming home.
… 運送回國的棺材出現在鏡頭上
That kind of story is a downer...
因為這樣會令人掃興…
...especially when you're getting ready for a party on a boat.
…特別是你准備在航空母艦上開晚會的時候
My fellow Americans...
同胞們…
...major combat operations in Iraq have ended.
…我們在伊拉克的大規模軍事行動已經結束
In the battle of Iraq...
在伊拉克戰場上…
...the United States and our allies have prevailed.
…美國和我們的盟友取得了勝利
Get out of the way!
讓開!
Move! Move! Move! Move!
快，快，快!
162, the number of troops killed by hostile fire.
162名士兵在交火中陣亡
- 244 U.S. Troops... - 384 U.S. Troops lost their lives...
-244名美國士兵-- -384名美國士兵犧牲--
- Total killed, 484. - Died in the line of duty, 500...
-一共陣亡484名 -500名犧牲--
631 American troops...
631名美國士兵--
More than 825 troops have been killed in Iraq.
超過825 名士兵在伊拉克陣亡
The largest number of American military deaths since Vietnam.
越戰之后陣亡最多的一次
There are some who feel like that if they attack us...
有些人會認為如果他們攻擊我們…
...that we may decide to leave prematurely.
…我們應該盡早撤離
They don't understand, if that's the case.
他們不了解情況
Let me finish.
讓我說完
There are some who feel like the conditions are such...
有些人認為他們能夠…
...that they can attack us there.
…對我們造成威脅
My answer is, bring them on.
我說，讓他們來吧
The United States was planning on walking through here...
政府計划就這么大搖大擺進來…
...like it was gonna be easy and all.
…好像很容易似的
But it's not that easy to conquer a country, is it?
征服一個國家并不容易，不是嗎?
The renewed battle for control of Iraq raged for a fourth day today...
爭奪伊拉克戰斗重新開始了，今天已經是第四天…
...with street clashes in nearly every corner of the country.
…這個國家的每一個角落都在發生街頭沖突
Iraq could become "another Vietnam."
伊拉克變成了“另一個越南”
Officials say they see evidence that Sunni and Shiite extremists...
有証據顯示遜尼派和什葉派極端分子…
...might be joining forces.
…也許已經開始聯合
They're not happy they're occupied.
他們不滿被占領的狀況
I wouldn't be happy if I were occupied either.
如果我被別國占領，我也會不滿
Two Japanese aid workers and a journalist...
兩名日本志愿者和一名記者…
...kidnapped by men calling themselves...
…被一個自稱“穆斯林聖戰旅”…
...the Mujahideen Squadrons.
…的組織綁架
They threatened to burn the hostages alive...
他們威脅如果日本不在三天內…
...if Japan does not withdraw its troops from Iraq within three days.
…從伊拉克撤軍，就把他們點天燈
What's happened?
到底怎么了?
They attacked our convoy.
他們襲擊我們的車隊
You wanna give us your name?
你叫什么名字?
Hamill, Thomas.
哈米爾，托馬斯
The Pentagon might keep up to 24,000 troops in combat...
國防部預計要讓24,000名士兵…
...beyond their tour.
…延長駐扎時間
I know our numbers in the military have gone down.
我知道駐軍人數在減少
They talk about retention.
他們在說要延長時間
I never expected to be deployed this long.
我沒有預料到要駐扎這么久
I don't think anybody did.
沒有人想到
I don't have any clue as to why we're still in Iraq.
真不知道我們為什么還要留在伊拉克
If Donald Rumsfeld was here, I'd ask him for his resignation.
如果唐納德 拉姆斯菲爾德來了 我會要求他辭職
With the war not going as planned...
戰爭進展不如人意…
...and the military in need of many more troops...
…需要更多的軍隊…
...where would they find the new recruits?
…到哪里去征兵呢?
Military experts say three times...
軍事專家稱需要三倍于…
...the 120,000 U.S. Troops now deployed...
…目前12萬駐軍的兵力…
...would be needed to pacify and rebuild the country.
…才能控制局面重建這個國家
They would find them all across America...
他們會在美國各地征兵…
...in the places that had been destroyed by the economy.
…在經濟被摧毀的地方
Places where one of the only jobs available...
在那些沒有工作可干…
...was to join the Army.
… 只有去參軍的地方
Places like my hometown of Flint, Michigan.
就像我的家鄉密歇根 弗林特
I was watching TV one day...
有一天我在看電視…
...and they showed some of the areas that had been hit by bombs.
…看到有些地方被炸彈襲擊
And while watching, I got to thinking...
當時我就想…
...there's parts of Flint that look like that.
…弗林特的一些地方也是如此
And we ain't been in a war.
但我們這里可不是戰場
Look at the neighborhood I live in.
看看我住的地方
Most of them are abandoned. You know, I mean...
大多數房屋被遺棄，我是說…
...that's not right. You wanna talk about terrorism?
…這是不對的，你要談恐怖主義?
Come right here. President Bush, right here. Come right here.
到這兒來，布什總統，就來這兒看
He knows about this corner. I e-mailed him.
他知道這個地方，我給他發了電子郵件
At the end of January of '04...
2004年1月末…
...the unemployment rate in Flint was 17 percent.
…弗林特的失業率是17％
But you have to take into consideration as well...
但是必須同時考慮…
...that when your unemployment runs out you're no longer counted.
…如果你失業超過一段時間 就不被計算在內了
I would say that we're close to at least 50 percent...
實際上是接近50％的人…
...not working or underemployed.
…沒有工作或者就業不充分
Because being underemployed is just as dangerous.
就業不充分同樣危險
My family has gone through the welfare system...
我的家庭曾經依靠過福利機構…
...when it was Job Central.
…那時候叫做職業中心
In the mid-'80s I came through the job training partnership program.
我在八十年代中期參加了就業培訓計划 （利拉 就業聯盟執行助理）
I went to a secretary school.
我去了秘書學校
Years later, I'm executive assistant to the president of the agency.
几年后，我成了這個機構的總裁助理
Interesting.
很有意思
My mother used to tell me all the time:
我母親以前一直對我說
"Why do you always go for the underdog?"
“你為什么一直在幫助失敗者?”
It was because the underdog is who needed me.
因為失敗者最需要我
People that don't have anything, that's who I have to fight for.
我要幫助的是那些一無所有的人
And that's who I have fought for my entire life.
我一生都在為他們奔走
I started taking my children and telling my children:
我開始對我的孩子說:
"The military is a good option.
參軍是個不錯的選擇
I can't afford to have you go to college. I can't pay your way.
我無法供你們上大學
Financial aid will not help you."
經濟援助也幫不了你們
So I, as a mother, started teaching my children...
因此，做為一個母親，我開始教孩子…
...about the options that the military could do.
…參軍也是一條出路
They would take them around the world.
可以環游世界
They'd see all the things that I, as a mother, couldn't let them see.
可以讓他們見識到 我這個做母親的沒辦法提供的東西
It'd pay for their education that I, as their mother and father, couldn't pay.
能夠為他們的教育籌到資金 而做為父母的我們卻不能
The military is a good option for kids in Flint.
對于弗林特人來說參軍是個不錯的選擇
The military is an excellent option for the people of Flint.
對于弗林特人來說參軍是個極好的選擇
How many of you have a friend or a family member in the service?
你們當中有多少人有朋友或者家人在軍隊服役?
Anybody currently serving overseas?
有在海外的嗎?
- A brother of mine. - My cousin.
-我的一個兄弟 -我的表兄
Yeah, cousin.
是的，表兄
- Where's your brother? - Iraq.
-你兄弟在哪兒? -伊拉克
Germany.
德國
My cousin got shipped off to Iraq, like, three days ago.
我表兄三天前開拔到伊拉克了
Dang.
該死
There's, like, an Army or Navy recruiter...
每個星期都有陸軍…
...or Marines recruiter up there almost every week...
…或者海軍，還有陸戰隊的人來征兵…
...in the lunchroom recruiting students at the lunchroom.
…就在學校的餐廳招募學生
There are people with a calling.
有一種職業
Most serve one weekend a month and two weeks a year.
一個月工作一個周末 一年工作兩個星期
Earning money for college.
能掙到大學的學費
Protecting their community.
還能保衛家鄉
In the Army National Guard...
參加國民衛隊…
...you can.
…你能做到
I'm going into the Air Force.
我要參加空軍
I'm gonna take a year off after high school.
高中畢業后當一年兵
And then make a career. I wanna be an aircraft maintenance technician.
然后開始工作，我想當飛機技師
I ran into a recruiter, and there was something I noticed about it.
我在碰到一個征兵員的時候發現一些事情
And this is kind of on another... I noticed it was odd.
我覺得有點…有點奇怪
More like he was hiring me than recruiting me for the Army.
他好像是在雇我而不是讓我參軍
It was the way he approached me. I was in Borders Books and Music.
我是說他接近我的方法 當時我在音樂書店
He came up like he was handing us a business card.
他走上來發給我名片
He had business cards made for the Army.
陸軍特制的名片
Meet Marine Staff Sergeant Dale Kortman...
認識一下海軍上士戴爾 考特曼…
...and Sergeant Raymond Plouhar.
…和雷蒙德 玻爾
They are two of the many recruiters assigned to Flint, Michigan.
他們是被派到弗林特的眾多征兵員中的兩位
They're very busy these days.
這些天他們很忙
Look, he's running away already.
看，他已經跑開了
- He's seen us coming. - Yeah.
-他看見我們了 -是的
What have we got here?
這個呢?
- Need a little gangster. - Yeah.
-要小流氓嗎？ -是的
We're heading over to the Courtland Mall right now.
我們現在去科特蘭商業街
They decided not to go to the wealthier...
他們不去郊區富人居住的…
...Genesee Valley Mall in the suburbs.
… 吉恩谷商業街
They have a hard time recruiting young people there.
在那里很難征到年輕人
Instead, they went to the other mall.
他們去了另一家商業街
- Let's go in through Mervyn's. - In through Mervyn's.
-我們去馬文斯百貨店 -馬文斯百貨店
And then we'll walk straight down and straight back and then go down...
去走一個來回，再去--
Gents, you know we're looking at you, right?
先生們，你們知道我們在找你們?
You guys ever think about joining up?
你們有沒有想過要參軍?
I thought about going to college and playing basketball.
我只想過上大學,打籃球
- You any good? - Yeah. Especially basketball.
-有沒有擅長的? -是的,特別是籃球
Good. You can play ball for the Marine Corps.
很好,你可以代表海軍陸站隊打球
Travel around the world for the Corps basketball team.
可以代表他們環游世界
- David Robinson was in the military. - Oh, was he?
-大衛羅賓遜就當過海軍 -哦,是嗎?
Yeah, you can definitely hook it up.
你可以跟他學
Right now somebody out there wants to be a Marine but has no idea how to.
現在還有人想當海軍卻不得其門呢
- Where you work at? - I work at KFC.
-你在哪兒上班? -肯德基
- Sweet. Hook us up with deals. - Yes.
-很好，我們可以推荐你 -好的
They're waiting to get recruited.
他們等著被征召
I was gonna try a career in music or something.
我想以后搞音樂什么的
Career in music? Maybe we can get you a career in music.
搞音樂?也許我們可以實現你的愿望
Let the Marines go for it. I'm sure you know who Shaggy is.
海軍可以幫你，你知道Shaggy吧
- You know anything about him? - Yeah, he's the Jamaican singer.
-聽說過他嗎? -是的,他是個牙買加歌手
How about a former Marine?
知不知道他當過海軍?
- Oh. - Did you know it?
-哦 -你知道嗎?
You need to know discipline if you're gonna get into music.
想搞音樂就必須先經過磨煉
Especially discipline with the money.
特別是金錢的磨煉
If you make a million, you need to manage that money.
如果你掙了一百萬,你就得學會理財
Come to the office, we can talk...
到辦公室來,我們可以談談…
...show you everything about the Marines.
…我告訴你所有海軍的事情
- A plan? - What you got going this afternoon?
-定下來好嗎? -今天下午有什么事情要做?
How about tomorrow? 10:00 Monday morning?
明天呢?明天早上10點?
- That sounds pretty good. - You want me to pick you up?
-很好 -要我們來接你嗎?
It's better to get them when they're in ones and twos...
最好是在他們三兩成群的時候截住他們…
...and work on them that way.
…就象剛才那樣做工作
Ladies, ready to join up?
女士們,要參軍嗎?
Green hat right behind us.
后面那個戴綠帽子的
- Looks young. He's young. - Yeah.
-看上去很年輕 -是的
We got two over here...
那邊還有兩個…
...right over by the red van.
…紅色面包車旁邊
You go that way, I go this way, we corner them.
你走那邊,我走這邊,我們截住他們
- You're in the ninth grade? - Yes, sir.
-你讀9年級? -是的,長官
Man, you look older than ninth grade.
你看上去要大一點
All right, here's my card.
好吧,這是我的名片
You ever thought about being a Marine, man?
有沒有想過參加海軍?
I've thought about it. I've got a wife and kid now.
想過,但我還有老婆孩子
Even more reason to join up.
有更多理由值得參軍
What I want to do, man...
伙計,實際上我是…
...is get information from you so I can scratch you off my list...
…我只是要你的資料 這樣就可以把你從名單上划掉…
...saying I've talked to you, and you're not interested. Is that cool?
…就說我已經和你談過了, 你不感興趣,行嗎?
What's your name? Phone number? What's your address?
你的名字,電話號碼,住址?
Add another one to the list.
在名單上再加一個
However, one would love to have that chance to experience college life.
人們都不想放過這個能上大學的機會
You know, stuff young people can do without having the risk...
有本事的年輕人不必冒生命威脅…
...of dying in the process, I guess I can say candidly.
…而又能達到目的，我說得夠坦率吧
The holidays add a bit more friction, as opposed to just another night...
節日的時候比平時沖突要多一點…
...in the fact we wanna give our guys a little time off, time to relax.
…因為我們想給士兵多一點時間休息，放松
However, we are in a combat zone, and my soldiers do recognize that fact.
然而我們是在交戰地區, 士兵也知道這個事實
Everybody's a little bit nervous about it, I guess.
我猜每個人都有點緊張
We're professionals. We're gonna take care of you.
我們是專家,我們會照顧你的
I promise.
我保証
Every house here has the right to have weapons.
這里的每間房子都可以保留武器
Maximum, one AK-47.
最多一柄AK-47
We always expect the targets to be armed.
我們總希望能瞄准目標
Rock 'n' roll.
出發了
These are fucking bolt cutters.
這些是斷線鉗
This goddamn thing to pry doors open.
這鬼東西是橇門用的
Pop this in there...
把它插進去…
Hey, Adele, just hold up.
嗨，阿黛爾，慢一點
No, no, no, no.
不,不,不
Where's she going?
她去哪兒?
- I'll go with her. - Where's she going?
-我和她一道去 -她去哪兒?
She's gonna call him.
她會給他電話的
She's gonna call him? No, no, no. Where is he at right now?
她會給他電話?不,不,不,他現在在哪兒?
Not on the phone.
不在電話上,不在電話上
Is he in the house?
在那屋子里嗎?
- Passerelli! Passerelli! - Is he in the house?
-帕塞雷里! 帕塞雷里! -他在屋子里嗎?
He is? He is in the house? Where?
在嗎?在屋子里?哪兒?
- This is him? - Get up there, second floor!
-是他嗎? -上去,到二樓去!
Watch out. Go, go, go! Watch out, Adele, watch out.
小心,上,上，阿黛爾，小心
I have one coming up.
有一個上來了
That's Suheib Al Douri?
那個是 蘇赫比 阿多里?
- What's your name? - Suheib.
-你叫什么? -蘇赫比
- This is Suheib. Yeah. - This is Suheib.
-是蘇赫比. 是的 -是蘇赫比
- This is Suheib? - Yeah.
-是蘇赫比? -是的
Stand him up. Get up.
讓他站起來
Tell them to calm down, please. We will not be long.
讓他們不要慌，不會很久的
We appreciate your cooperation. This is the target.
謝謝你們的合作，這就是我要找的人
Suheib Al Douri. Bring him out.
蘇赫比 阿多里.帶出來
We have to, as you go back to the old saying...
有句老話，我們必須
...win the hearts and minds of the people. That's our job.
…贏得他們的心，這就是我們的工作
We have to... We have to bring the...
我們必須-- 必須--
The ideal of democracy and freedom to the country...
把民主和自由的觀念帶入這個國家…
...and show them that the American people are not here to rule Iraq.
…給他們看，我們美國人不是來統治伊拉克
I start doing evidence turn-in. That process takes about three hours.
我們先要分析線報，這就要花三個小時
So that's gonna be it for the night.
這樣一個晚上就沒有了
That concludes Christmas Eve.
包括聖誕夜
Merry Christmas, PRT. Merry Christmas.
士兵們，聖誕快樂
Santa came to Iraq just for you guys.
聖誕老人為了你們來到了伊拉克
Trying to keep skies clear for you, Santa.
為你們掃除天空的陰霾
Do you consider yourself a proud American?
你為自己是美國人驕傲嗎?
Absolutely.
當然
I'm an extremely proud American. I'm probably more proud...
實際上我非常驕傲…
...than the average Joe.
…也許比一般人都強烈
When I put my flag out, I can't allow it to touch the ground.
我甚至不允許讓國旗碰到地面
Because I know the lives that were lost and the blood that was shed...
因為我知道戰士們在外拋頭顱洒熱血…
...so that I could be here and have a flag.
…我們才能在家挂國旗
- How often do you put the flag out? - Every single day. Every day.
-你一般多長時間挂一次? -每天
I started when my daughter was in Desert Storm.
從我女兒參軍“沙漠風暴”行動開始
I had the same flag...
國旗每天都飄揚在我的門廊前…
...flying on my front porch and the same yellow ribbons.
…還有那黃絲帶
Praying and hoping every day that my child would come home safe.
我每天都祈禱我的孩子能平安歸來
And everybody's child would come home safe.
每家的孩子都能平安歸來
- And she did.
-她回來了
Have other family members been in the military?
家里還有其它人當兵嗎?
Absolutely. Uncles, aunts...
當然，叔叔們 阿姨們…
...cousins, brothers, father.
…表親，兄弟，父親
- Very strong military family. - Very strong.
-很堅強的家庭 -很堅強
My family was... My family is what I consider...
我的家庭-- 我認為我的家庭…
...part of the backbone of America.
…就是美國的脊梁
It's families like mine. And it's not just my family.
不僅僅是我們一家
There's hundreds of families, millions of families...
還有很多家庭，上百萬的家庭…
...that this country was founded on their backs.
…我們的國家就是建立在他們的脊梁上
I have been known to be a conservative Democrat. Yeah.
我一直是保守的民主黨人
That's what you consider yourself? Yeah.
－你是這樣看自己的？ －是的
- Yeah, it's a great country. - It's a great country. A great country.
-是的，這是一個偉大的國家 -一個偉大的國家，偉大
The cross that I choose to wear is a multicultural, multicolor cross.
我這個十字架代表多文化和多種族
That's because I believe that all God's people come in many colors.
因為我相信所有膚色的人都是上帝的子民
And my family itself is multicultural.
我的家庭本身就是多文化的
You have a daughter who went into the military.
你女兒當過兵
Then your first-born son, in the military.
你的長子現在在當兵
That's quite a gift to the country from your family.
你的家庭對國家真是貢獻頗多
So having a son in the Army, pretty proud thing.
有一個當兵的兒子是非常值得驕傲的
Oh, you know what? He made it.
哦，他成功了
What was your reaction to protestors during the Gulf War or Vietnam?
你對海灣戰爭和越南戰爭間發生的 反戰示威是什么反應?
I always hated the protestors.
我以前痛恨那些示威者
It was just a slap in my face.
恨他們，就像給了我一耳光
It was just like they were dishonoring my son.
他們是在丟我兒子的人
And I burned in my soul to tell them, "You don't understand.
我迫切想對他們說，你們不明白
They're not there because they wanna be there."
他們不是想去打仗才去的
But then I came to understand they weren't protesting the men...
后來我認識到他們不是抗議那些士兵…
...and women there. They were protesting the concept of the war.
…是反對這個國家對戰爭的理念
I know I'm a soldier, and I'm here to do a job.
我是個士兵，我在履行我的職責
I've been a soldier for a while.
我當兵有些年頭了
Once you have to go and do your job...
一旦你當了兵…
...and you see the things that you see...
…你所看到的…
...I was saying, there's some disillusionment in that.
…我是說，有時候有種幻滅的感覺
Battalion commander fully expects us to be...
指揮官們希望我們…
...attacked in some type of way...
…在接觸到汽油彈之前…
...before we get to FARP Shell.
…能受到某種程度的襲擊
I know that so far it's been pretty calm.
直到目前都很平靜
Not much has happened.
沒多少事情發生
But be aware that it can, and it probably will.
當他們認識到最終無可避免的時候
They're beginning to organize themselves, just in neighborhoods.
他們就開始組織起來
The kids get together a lot. Well, I can't say kids...
那些孩子們組織起來… 不能說是孩子
...but guys about 17, 18...
…是十七八歲的年輕人…
...starting to come together.
…他們開始聚集起來
They hate us. Why, I'm not really sure.
他們恨我們，我不知道為什么
Immoral behavior breeds immoral behavior.
不道德的行為滋生了不道德的行為
When a president commits the immoral act...
總統做出了不道德的行為…
...of sending otherwise good kids to war based on a lie...
…基于謊言把這些 原本是好孩子的士兵送去戰場…
...this is what you get.
… 后果就是這樣
Hey, is he ticklish?
他怕痒痒嗎?
Don't tell me you don't know.
別說你不知道
To have these people shoot at us, kill us, blow us up...
他們向我們開槍，扔炸彈…
...whatever, means they can.
…無所不用其極
And I don't understand it.
我不明白
We're trying to help these people, and it seems...
我們為什么還有幫助他們…
...they don't want our help. "Get out of here!"
…他們似乎不需要我們的幫助 “滾回去!”
The minute something goes wrong, "Why weren't you here?
如果出了什么岔子，就有人說 你為什么不在那里?
Why didn't you do this?" You know, it's...
為什么沒這么做? 真是--
I hate this country.
我恨這個國家
You know, you... I feel that a part of your soul...
我覺得當你奪去別人生命的時候…
...is destroyed in taking another life.
…你覺得自己的靈魂被毀滅了
Yeah, that statement is very true.
舉刀殺人，自己也難獨善其身
You cannot kill someone without killing a part of yourself.
這句話說得很對
If you get called up...
如果你被征召…
...will you go back to Iraq? - No.
-…你還會回伊拉克嗎? -不會
What repercussions do you face if you don't?
如果你不去，會有什么后果呢?
Possible jail time.
也許要坐牢
That's one possible thing.
有可能
- Are you willing to risk that? - Yes.
-你愿意冒這個險? -是的
Yes, l...
是的，我--
I will not let my person...
我不會允許自己…
I will not let anyone...
允許任何人…
...send me back over there to kill other poor people.
…送我回去屠殺那些可憐的人
Especially when they pose no threat to me and my country.
特別是他們對我和我的國家并沒有造成威脅
I won't do it.
我不會那么做的
This is an impressive crowd. The haves...
人真不少，有產階級…
...and the have-mores.
…和更有產階級
Some people call you the elite.
有人說你們是精英
I call you my base.
我們說你們是我的基石
While Bush was busy taking care of his base...
布什一邊忙于關心他的基石…
...and professing his love for our troops...
…一邊表示熱愛他的士兵…
...he proposed cutting combat soldiers' pay by 33 percent...
…同時他又建議給作戰士兵削減33％的工資…
...and assistance to their families by 60 percent.
…削減60％給軍屬的補貼
He opposed giving veterans...
反對給退伍軍人…
...a billion dollars more in health-care benefits...
…增加10億美元的醫療保健資金…
...and he supported closing veteran hospitals.
…支持關閉退伍軍人醫院
He tried to double the prescription drug costs for veterans...
試圖把退伍軍人處方藥的成本加倍…
...and opposed full benefits for part-time reservists.
…反對給預備役軍人發全薪
When Staff Sergeant Brett Petriken from Flint...
弗林特的布來特 帕金肯…
...was killed in Iraq on May 26th...
… 5月26日在伊拉克陣亡之后…
...the Army sent his last paycheck to his family...
… 陸軍把他最后一個月的工資寄回家…
...but they docked him for the last five days of the month he didn't work...
…卻扣除了最后5天的工資…
...because he was dead.
…因為他死了，缺勤
They say they're not gonna leave any veteran behind...
他們說不會漏掉一個退伍軍人…
...but they're leaving all kinds of veterans behind.
…但他們把所有的退伍軍人都漏掉了
To say we're forgotten, I know we're not. But missed? Yes.
與其說我們被遺忘了，不如說是遺漏了
Yes. There's a lot of soldiers that have been missed...
是的，有很多士兵被遺漏了…
...that have been skipped over.
…忽略了
Didn't get the proper coverage they deserved.
沒有得到他們應得的照料
There's a death toll, but not showing the injured or amputated.
只有死亡人員名單，沒有傷殘名單 （戰爭的前13個月有將近5000名士兵受傷）
- I still feel like I have hands. - Yeah.
-我覺得自己的手還在 -嗯
And the pain is like my hands are being crushed in a vise.
好像鉗子在夾我的手那么疼
But they do a lot to help it...
但他們幫了我很多…
...and they take a lot of the edge off it.
…減輕了我很多痛楚
It makes it a lot more tolerable.
讓我覺得容易忍受點了
I was injured in late April on patrol in Baghdad.
我是4月末在巴格達巡邏的時候受傷的
A couple of guys come out and ambushed us.
一幫人跳出來伏擊我們
I got nerve damage and stuff like that.
我的神經受了傷
I've got a lot of pain. I'm constantly in pain.
一直受到傷痛折磨
I take a lot of morphine...
服用了很多嗎啡…
...to help with that and stuff.
…來止痛
I'm doing...
我在--
Doing... You know, just readjusting.
在調整
Getting life back on track.
想回到原來的生活軌跡上去
You know what I'm saying?
你懂我意思嗎?
I'm not gonna do what it is that I did before.
我不會再做以前做的事情了
I was a Republican for quite a few years.
我很長一段時間是共和黨人
And...
出于…
...for some reason, they...
…出于某種原因，他們…
They conduct business in a very dishonest way.
他們采用了非常不光彩的手段
I'm gonna be incredibly active in the Democratic Party...
等我一恢復，…
...down where I live once I get out.
…我就會去幫助民主黨
I'm gonna definitely do my best...
我會盡力…
...to ensure that the Democrats win control.
…幫助民主黨獲勝
Iraq, Baghdad, I didn't know anything of those things.
伊拉克，巴格達，我對這些根本一無所知
And we were in the hallway in the upstairs of our house...
我在樓上走廊遇到他…
...and he was crying and said that he was really scared.
…他在苦，說他很害怕
And he didn't want to have to go to Iraq.
他不想去伊拉克
So we had a conversation about, sometimes some fear is healthy...
我們進行了交談，有時候恐懼也是健康的…
...because it keeps our senses about us.
…讓人變得理智
That's when he told me he hadn't told anybody else.
他告訴我他從沒對別人說過
But he knew he was going to Baghdad.
但他知道他要去巴格達了
We were... As everybody, we were glued to the TV.
我們每個人天天都盯著電視
Just glued, completely glued to the television...
完全忘記了其它事情…
...in hopes of seeing a glimpse of him.
…希望能看到他
"Can't you please go to where the helicopters are?
快到直升機旁邊去啊
Can't you please let us see him?"
讓我們看看你啊
Then that night, it was about 10 something...
那天晚上大約10點多…
...I went upstairs to the bedroom.
…我上樓准備睡覺
I was in bed, flipping the channels with the remote.
躺在床上隨手換著頻道
All I heard was, "Black Hawk down, South Central Iraq."
我聽到，“伊拉克中南部，黑鷹直升機墜落”
What I can tell you at this hour is that last night...
昨天晚上…
...the Army did, indeed, lose a Black Hawk helicopter.
…陸軍損失了一架黑鷹直升機
We are being told by officers on the ground...
地面人員稱…
...that there were six occupants inside the Black Hawk.
…上面總共用6名乘客
The next morning I got up, and I said:
第二早上，我說:
"You push those sad thoughts out of your mind.
別再想這些可怕的事情了
Okay, Jesus, I need you to come in.
耶穌啊，幫幫我吧
I need you, Jesus. You gotta help me through this."
我需要你，耶穌，幫我渡過難關
The Army called me, and I remember getting on the phone and him saying...
陸軍打電話給我，我記得拿起電話--
Asking me was I Lila Lipscomb, and I said, "Yes."
他問我是不是麗拉 立普斯科, 我回答“是的”
And he said, "Mother of Sergeant Michael Pedersen?"
他說，“麥克佩德森的母親?”
And I remember dropping the telephone.
電話從我手中滑落
And all I can honestly say that I remember...
我只記得他說…
...is, "Ma'am, the United States Army...
… 夫人，美國陸軍…
...the secretary of defense regretfully informs you..."
…國防部長遺憾地通知您--
That's all I know.
我就記得這些
The grief grabbed me so hard...
巨大的悲痛包圍著我…
...that I literally fell on the floor.
…我一下子摔到了地上
And I was alone. I didn't have anybody to pick me up.
我一個人，沒人扶我起來
So I literally crawled over to my desk...
我掙扎著爬到桌子上…
...and was hanging on.
…趴在上面
And I remember screaming:
我記得我喊到:
"Why does it have to be Michael?
為什么是麥克?
Why did you have to take my son? Why is it my son you had to take?
你為什么要奪走我的兒子?
He didn't do anything.
他沒做什么錯事
He wasn't a bad guy. He was a good guy.
他不是壞人，是個好人
Why did you have to take my son?"
為什么要奪走我的兒子?
L... l... l... I'm...
我-- 我-- 我--
I can't imagine what it must be like to lose a son or a daughter...
我不能想象失去兒女是什么樣子的…
...or a husband and... Or a wife, for that matter.
…或者失去丈夫或--妻子
And l... It pains me.
而我--那讓我感到悲痛
Do you have his last letter?
你有他最后的一封信嗎?
It was mailed March 16th...
這封信是3月16日寄出的…
...but I didn't get it until probably a week before he was killed.
…但是大概在他死前一個星期我才收到
"Hello. Hey, Mama.
你好,嗨,媽媽
Well, sorry I haven't been able to call.
嗯,對不起我沒能打電話給您
They took the phone seven days ago.
他們7天前就把電話拿走了
I got the letter and box.
我收到了你的信和盒子
That is so cool. Your first grandson came...
您的第一個孫子出世了…真是太棒了
...the same day your oldest son did.
…而且是跟你的大兒子同一天生日
How is everyone? I'm doing fine.
大家都怎么樣?我過得很好
We are just out here in the sand and windstorms waiting.
我們現在只是在沙塵和暴風中等待命令
What in the world is wrong with George?
喬治他到底是有什么毛病?
Trying to be like his dad, Bush.
想跟他父親布什一樣
He got us out here for nothing whatsoever.
他派我們到這里來毫無意義
I am so furious right now, Mama.
我現在真的很憤怒,媽媽
I really hope they do not re-elect that fool, honestly.
老實說,我真的希望他們不要讓那個傻瓜連任
I am in good spirits, and I am doing okay.
我現在精神很好,一切正常
I really miss you guys.
我真的很相信大家
Thanks for the Bible...
謝謝您寄來的聖經…
...and books and candy.
…還有書和糖果
I really look forward to letters from you guys.
我真的期待再收到你們大家的信
Well, tell all the family hello and that I am doing fine.
嗯,向家里所有人問好,告訴他們我過得很好
We don't expect anything to happen any time soon.
我們覺得最近也不會有什么事情發生
I cannot wait to get home and get back to my life.
我都等不及要回家,回來過我自己的生活
Tell Sputnik congrats...
告訴斯波汀我恭喜…
...and I'll see my first nephew soon...
…我很快就會回來看我的第一個侄子…
...as soon as I get back to the States.
…一回到美國我就會回家
Hope you guys are doing okay...
希望你們大家一切平安…
...and keep sending the mail.
…記得給我寫信
It makes getting through the days easier.
那讓這里的日子好熬一些
Well, I am on my way to bed...
嗯,我要去睡覺了…
...so I will write you guys soon.
…很快我就會再給你們寫信的
I love and miss...
我愛你們大家…
...all of you guys."
…想念你們
I want him to be alive...
我想要他還活著…
...and I can't make him alive.
…但是我不能讓他復活
But your flesh just aches.
但是你的心確實會疼
You want your child. It's out of sync.
你要你的孩子.這是完全不對的
A parent is not supposed to bury their child.
父母不應該去埋葬自己的孩子
I feel... I feel sad for my family...
我--我為我的家人感到悲哀…
...because we lost our son.
…因為我們失去了兒子
But...
但是…
...I really feel sorry for the other families...
…我真的為那些其他的家庭…
...that is losing their kids as we speak.
…那些正在失去他們的孩子的家庭,感到悲哀
And for what?
并且他們是為了什么而死?
L... I don't...
我--我不知道--
That's the... I guess the sickening part.
那個才是--我想才是讓人惡心的地方
For what?
為了什么?
You've heard a lot about Halliburton lately.
你們最近聽說了關于哈里伯頓公司的很多事 （戴夫 萊瑟哈里伯頓公司CEO）
Criticism is okay. We can take it. Criticism is not failure.
批評是沒事的.我們能接受 批評不是失敗
Our employees are doing a great job.
我們的員工工作得很出色
We're feeding the soldiers. We're rebuilding Iraq.
我們在供給士兵們食物. 我們在重建伊拉克
Will things go wrong? Sure they will. It's a war zone.
會出現問題嗎?當然會.但那里是戰區
We're serving the troops because of what we know...
我們能為我們的軍隊服務 是因為我們的專業知識…
...not who we know.
…而不是因為我們認識某個人
Let me tell you about Halliburton, the company I ran.
讓我來談談哈里伯頓公司,由我管理的公司
I'm proud of what I did at Halliburton.
我為我在哈里伯頓公司所做的事情感到驕傲
The people are proud of what they've accomplished. I, frankly...
我們的員工為他們所取得的成績而驕傲. 而我,老實說…
...don't feel any need to apologize...
…并不覺得有必要作出道歉…
...for the way I've spent my time over the last five years...
…為我在過去5年里的所作所為…
...as the CEO and chairman of a major American corporation.
…作為一個美國大公司的首席執行官和主席
This is also an attempt to divert attention...
這也是一個企圖轉移注意力的行動…
...from the fact they have no energy policy.
…讓人們不再關注他們沒有能源政策的事實
And as the secretary of energy said, "We were caught unawares."
正如能源部長所說,“我們被打了個措手不及”
In the middle of the war, Microsoft, DHL and other corporations...
在戰爭期間,微軟,DHL還有其他的公司…
...invited Halliburton to a conference...
…邀請哈里伯頓公司參加一個會議…
...to figure out how much money could be made in Iraq.
…來確認在伊拉克能賺到多少錢
Having worked this...
你們為此所做的努力…
...effort, even since before the... The invasion...
…甚至在入侵… （麥克 梅里美國陸軍工程兵團公司）
...the liberation of Iraq started.
…解放伊拉克之前就已經開始了
You, industry, are definitely a vital part of that effort.
你們絕對是不可或缺的力量
We appreciate your interest in this. We need you.
我們感激你們對此事的興趣.我們需要你們
Lots of you are small businesses and struggling:
你們當中有很多公司規模很小,正在拼搏向上 （尤素夫 斯萊曼伊拉克背景的哈里斯公司）
"How do we get a piece of this? You big guys are gonna get it.
我們怎樣才能從中分到一杯羹? 你們中的大公司會得到合約
The rest of us will have subcontracting capability or none at all."
其他人將有得到轉包的機會或者一點機會也沒有
USTDA is for you.
美國貿易和開發署是為你們服務的
Once that oil starts flowing...
一旦石油開始開采…
...and money coming, gonna be lots of money.
…錢就會滾滾而來,很多錢
It's the second-largest reserve of oil in the world.
那里是世界上第二大石油儲藏地
No question of how much money's there.
那些能賺很多錢是毫無疑問的
I've been getting complaints from Iraqi firms and American firms.
我一直都有聽到伊拉克公司和美國公司的報怨 （山姆 庫巴博士美國伊拉克商會）
The lack of transparency, the corruption.
說什么缺乏透明度,腐敗
I think the profits American companies are making, the main companies...
我覺得美國公司現在所賺得的利潤 那些主要的公司…
...are so overwhelming.
…是不可估量的
I mean, when you have a line item for a million dollars...
我是說,如果你手頭上有個總價100萬美元的合同…
...and you subcontract it out for 50 or 60 or $70,000...
…而你以許多五十萬或者六十萬 七十萬美元的價格分包出去…
...that's a huge profit.
…那個利潤是巨大的
It's the American taxpayer that's gonna pay for that.
最終將是由美國的納稅人來為此買單
And it's gonna get better. Start building relationships.
而且情況將會好轉 開始建造關系網吧
Because it's gonna get much better...
因為情況將會變得好得多…
...as the oil flows and their budgets increase.
…在石油開始開采,并且他們的預算增加了的時候
Good news is, whatever it costs, the government will pay you.
好消息是,不管要花費多少, 政府都會為此買單
War is always good for certain companies...
戰爭對某些公司而言總是好的…
...that are in the war... The business of war.
…那些參與戰爭--戰爭生意的公司
We're very proud.
我們非常驕傲 （喬治 西格拉斯 哈里伯頓公司副總裁）
Supporting U.S. Government and military.
我們支持著美國政府和軍隊
The real heroes of the campaign and the reconstruction...
戰役和重建中的真正英雄…
...are the men and women of the U.S. Armed Forces.
…是美國軍方的男男女女們
We're proud of being any part we can in supporting them.
我們對我們有機會支持他們而感到驕傲
Halliburton delivers hot meals, supplies, clean clothing...
哈里伯頓公司給士兵們 送去熱飯菜,供給,干淨衣服…
...and communications to our soldiers...
…以及通訊設備…
...so they can be a little closer to home.
…讓他們感覺離家更近一些
It's a girl!
是個女孩!
Halliburton. Proud to serve our troops.
哈里伯頓公司. 驕傲的為我們的軍隊服務
I just read in the paper Halliburton got another contract.
我剛剛看到報紙上說 哈里伯頓公司又得到了一個合同
- Halliburton got another contract. - That's right.
-哈里伯頓公司又得到了一個合同 -對
Which is not being...
而且根本沒有…
...contested at all.
…一點競爭
Because nobody knows.
因為沒有人知道
Well, it's in the paper, so somebody knows.
嗯,現在報紙上登了,肯定有人知道的
But that's after it happens, after the fact. It's too late.
但那是在事情發生了之后, 木已成舟,已經太遲了
The United States is now a major player in the Iraqi oil business.
美國現在在伊拉克石油生意中扮演著重要的角色
American troops guard the oil fields...
美國軍隊,守衛著油田…
...as Texas oil workers assess their potential.
…當德克薩斯的石油工人們在估算石油儲量的時候
It's a safe environment to work in. We don't feel any risk.
我們的工作環境很安全,一點都不覺得危險
We feel we're being well protected here, or we wouldn't be here.
我們覺得自己受到了良好的保護, 不然我們也不會來了
It's no secret. I mean...
這不是秘密.我是說…
...I make anywhere between 2 and 3000 a month.
…我一個月掙大概2到3千元
A Halliburton employee out here driving a bus...
這里的一個開汽車的哈里伯頓公司員工…
...can make between 8 and 10,000 a month. Explain that one to me.
…一個月能掙8千到1萬.你說怎么解釋?
For 40 hours a week.
他們一周只要工作40個小時
Driving the same two-and-half-mile route.
只要在同一條2.5英里的路上開來開去
Go figure.
去想想吧
Where's the justification in that?
公平何在?
There's no other single area of the world today...
在當今世界沒有任何一個其它地方… （戈登 波比特 卡爾瑪分銷中心）
...with the opportunity for business, new business...
…有著如此的商機,新的商機…
...similar to the opportunity that's available today in Iraq.
…能跟伊拉克現在的商機相比
The president went in, did what he did.
總統參加了,他做了他應做的事 （格蘭特 哈伯美國創新公司）
We're supporting him and our troops.
我們支持他和我們的軍隊
We wanna make sure that the efforts and the lost lives...
我們要保証那些努力和失去的生命…
...wasn't for no reason.
…沒有白費
If it wasn't for the oil, nobody would be there.
如果不是因為石油,沒有人會去那里
Nobody would worry about it.
甚至沒有人關心那里
Unfortunately, at least for the near term...
不幸的是,至少從短期來看… （布萊恩 奧博 保鏢公司）
...we think it's gonna be a good situation, a dangerous situation.
…我們覺得那里會是個好形勢 同時也是危險的形勢
Good for business, bad for the people.
對做生意來說很好,對那里的人民來說不好
Today on the news, Rumsfeld was saying...
今天拉姆斯菲爾德說--
And Wolfowitz was saying:
沃爾福茲（美國國防部助理國務卿）也說:
"The Iraqi people are much, much better off.
伊拉克人民現在生活狀況要好得多了
Isn't it better that we got rid of Saddam...
現在我們除掉了薩達姆…
...and now the Iraqi people can do what they wanna do...
…伊拉克人民可以做他們想做的事了…
...and really be free?"
…得到了真正的自由,那不是好很多嗎?
Will they ever be free? No, they'll not be free.
他們會有機會得到自由嗎? 不,他們不會得到自由的
And where are the weapons of mass destruction?
還有那些大規模殺傷性武器在哪里呢?
It was a... We were duped. We were really duped.
那個--我們被耍了,真的被耍了
And these poor people...
還有這些可憐的人們…
...the young men and women who are being killed there.
…那些被奪去生命的年輕人
- It's unnecessary. - That's a disgrace.
-那是不必要的 -那真讓人惡心
- That's it. No more.
-夠了,不要再說了
They died in a just cause, for defending freedom...
他們是為了保衛自由這樣的崇高理想而獻身…
...and they will not have died in vain.
…他們的血不會白流的
Lila had called to tell me she was coming down from Flint...
麗拉打電話跟我說她要從弗林特…
...to Washington, D. C. To attend a jobs conference.
…來華盛頓特區開會
On her break, she said she was going to go...
有空的話,她說她要去…
...and pay a visit to the White House.
…看一看白宮
Bush killed children. Iraqi children.
布什殺了小孩.伊拉克的小孩
- My son, killed. - Killed my people in Spain, yesterday.
-我的兒子,也死了 -他昨天在西班牙殺了我的家人
- Lies kill people. Your children too. - Yes, my son.
-諾言是會殺人的.包括你的孩子 -是的,我的兒子
They have no business to do in Iraq now. They're killing...
他們現在在伊拉克已經無事可做了. 他們在殺害…
...all these young Americans. - Yes.
-…所有這些年輕的美國孩子 -是的
For what? For oil. Bush is a terrorist.
為了什么?為了石油.布什是恐怖分子
- No, he isn't. This is all staged. - Yes, he is.
-不,他不是的.她是在演戲 -是,他是恐怖分子
- This is all staged. - My son.
-她是在演戲 -我的兒子
- Where was he killed? - You tell me my son is not a stage.
-他死在哪里的? -你告訴我我兒子的死不是演戲!
- He was killed in Karbala.
-他在哪里死的? -他死在卡巴拉
April 2nd. It's not a stage. My son is dead.
4月2日.那不是演戲.我的兒子死了
There are a lot of other people too.
那里也死了很多其他人的
Blame al Qaeda.
要怪就怪基地
What did that woman yell at you?
那個女人跟你嚷什么?
That I'm supposed to blame the al Qaeda.
說我應該去怪基地
The al Qaeda didn't make a decision to send my son to Iraq.
并不是基地決定派我兒子去伊拉克的
Ignorance that we deal with, with everyday people.
我們所面對的無知,那些普通人的無知
Because they don't know. People think they know...
因為他們不了解真相 大家以為自己了解了…
...but you don't know. I thought I knew, but I didn't know.
…但他們并不了解 我曾覺得我了解,但事實也并非如此
I need my son.
我需要我的兒子
God, it's tougher than I thought it was gonna be...
上帝啊,這比我想象中的還要艱難…
...to be here.
…來到這里
But it's freeing also...
但這也讓我感到釋放了…
...because I finally have a place...
…因為我終于有了一個地方…
...to put all my pain and all my anger...
…可以把我所有的痛苦了怒火…
...and to release it.
…通通釋放在那里
I guess I was tired of seeing people like Lila Lipscomb suffer.
我想我厭倦了看到象麗拉 立普斯科受苦了
Especially when, out of the 535 members of Congress...
尤其是當,在535個國會議員中…
...only one had an enlisted son in Iraq.
…只有一個人把兒子送往伊拉克
I asked Corporal Henderson of the United States Marine Corps...
我讓美國海軍陸戰隊的亨德森下士…
...to join me on Capitol Hill...
…跟我一起去國會山…
...to see how many members of Congress we could convince...
…去看看我們能說服多少國會議員…
...to enlist their children to go to Iraq.
…去把自己的兒子送往伊拉克參軍
Congressman, I'm Michael Moore.
議員,我是邁克爾 摩爾
- Hey, Michael. How are you doing? - Good.
-嗨，邁克爾. 你好嗎? -好
- John Tanner, from Tennessee. - Very nice to meet you.
-約翰 唐納，田納西州的 -很高興認識您
- What y'all doing? - I'm here with Corporal Henderson.
-你們在干什么? -我是跟亨德森下士一起來的
- United States Marine Corps. - Corporal, I was in the Navy.
-他是美國海軍陸戰隊的 -下士,我參加過海軍的
- 1968 to '72. - Okay.
-1968年到72年 -好
We had Marines guarding the base.
我們的基地有陸戰隊員把守
- You have kids? - Yeah.
-你有孩子嗎? -有
Is there any way we can get them to enlist...
你看我們有沒有可能送他們參軍…
...and go over there and help out with the effort?
…并且把他們送到伊拉克去幫忙?
- I've got all the brochures. - One of them has got two children.
-我有所有的宣傳小冊子 -其中有一個有兩個孩子
See, there's not many congressmen that have kids over there.
看,沒有多少議員有孩子在那邊
In fact, only one. You know.
事實上,只有一個,你知道嗎?
So we just thought maybe they...
所以我們只是想也許他們--
- You guys should send your kids first. - That's right.
-你們應該首先把孩子送過去 -對
- What do you think about that? - I don't disagree.
-你覺得怎么樣? -我并非不同意
You don't? Oh, good. Well, take some brochures.
你同意?噢,好.那把這些冊子拿去吧
- At least take a Marine brochure. - Thank you.
-至少拿一本陸戰隊的宣傳冊吧 -謝謝
- Pass it around. - Yeah, well...
-幫我傳一傳 -好,嗯…
Encourage the fellow members if they're for the war to get behind it.
鼓勵那些支持戰爭的同仁把孩子們給戰爭一些支持
- Send their own. - Thank you.
-把他們的自己孩子派去 -謝謝
Thank you, sir. Thank you very much.
謝謝您,先生.非常感謝
Congressman? Michael Moore.
議員?邁克爾 摩爾
- How you doing today? - Good.
-你今天好嗎? -好
I'm trying to get members of Congress to get their kids to enlist in the Army...
我正在嘗試讓國會的議員們送自己的孩子去參軍…
...and go over to Iraq.
…然后去伊拉克參戰
Congressman.
議員
Congressman Castle?
卡薩議員?卡薩議員?
Congressman. Congressman.
議員.議員
Congressman Doolittle, Michael Moore.
多利多議員 邁克爾 摩爾
I was wondering if...
我在想--
Is there any way to?
有沒有可能…?
Of course, not a single member of Congress...
當然,沒有任何一個國會議員…
...wanted to sacrifice their child for the war in Iraq.
…愿意為了伊拉克戰爭犧牲他們的孩子
And who could blame them?
而誰又能責怪他們呢?
Who would wanna give up their child?
有誰又會放棄自己的孩子?
Would you?
你會嗎?
Would he?
他會嗎?
I've always been amazed that the very people...
我一直對于那些…
...forced to live in the worst parts of town...
…被迫生活在城市最差地段的人們感到驚訝…
...go to the worst schools and who have it the hardest...
…他們上的是最差的學校,生活得最艱難…
...are always the first to step up to defend that very system.
…但他們總是第一個站出來來保衛 那令他們受苦受難的系統
They serve so that we don't have to.
他們去服役,所以我們就不必去
They offer to give up their lives so that we can be free.
他們愿意獻出自己的生命,而 讓我們獲得自由
It is remarkable, their gift to us.
他們給我們的禮物是非凡的
And all they ask for in return...
而他們所要求的回報…
...is that we never send them into harm's way...
…僅僅是我們不要故意去傷害他們…
...unless it's absolutely necessary.
…除非逼不得已
Will they ever trust us again?
他們還會信任我們嗎?
He had used weapons.
他擁有使用過的武器
We know where they are.
我們知道他們在哪里
Around Tikrit, Baghdad and east, west, south and north.
在提克里克，巴格達附近,東南西北都有
There is a tie between Iraq and what happened on 9/11.
伊拉克和911事件有著聯系
The struggle can only end...
他們的掙扎只有在…
...with their complete and permanent destruction.
…受到永久性毀滅之后才會停止
We wage a war to save civilization itself.
我們為了人類文明而發動戰爭
We did not seek it.
我們并不是為了戰爭而戰爭
But we will fight it, and we will prevail.
但是我們將要努力戰斗,而且我們將勝利
George Orwell once wrote...
喬治．奧威爾曾經寫道…
...that, "It's not a matter of whether the war is not real or if it is.
…問題不是在于戰爭本身是不是師出有名
Victory is not possible.
勝利是不可能的
The war is not meant to be won. It is meant to be continuous.
我們并不可能贏得戰爭,它只可能持續下去
A hierarchical society is only possible...
一個等級社會的存在…
...on the basis of poverty and ignorance.
…是建立在貧困和無知的基礎上的
This new version is the past...
這是過去的翻版…
...and no different past can ever have existed.
…而且與過去所發生的事情毫無區別
In principle, the war effort is always planned...
大體上說,發動的戰爭的目的…
...to keep society on the brink of starvation.
…就是保証社會處于飢荒的邊緣
The war is waged by the ruling group against its own subjects.
戰爭是統治集團發起的用于達到 自己的目的的工具
And its object is not the victory over either Eurasia or East Asia...
而它的目的不是對歐亞大陸或者東亞的勝利…
...but to keep the very structure of society intact."
…而是維持當今的社會結構.
There's an old saying in T ennessee.
田納西州有句老話
I know it's in T exas, probably in Tennessee.
我是在德克薩斯聽說的,也可能是在田納西
Fool me once...
愚弄我一次…
...shame on...
…可恥的是…
Shame on you.
可恥的是你
You fool me, we can't get fooled again.
你愚弄我,我們是不可能再被愚弄的
For once, we agreed.
我們第一次意見相同了